Alright, so we are going to now
incorporate
velocity into our kinematics questions.
Sorry, acceleration. So acceleration, as
we
know, is how fast velocity changes over
time.
And before we even get started on
acceleration
questions, we already have some formulas
that
are pre-built that can help us with a lot
of
these physics questions. They're usually
given
to us or memorized on the exam.
For example, AP Physics 1 has the formula
sheet
for it, and these are the three key
formulas.
I'm going to put it in red. First one is,
whoa.
First one is v of x equals v of x-initial
plus
a of x times t.
So, what does this mean? Well, v of x is
the
velocity, v of x-initial is the initial
velocity,
initial velocity, a
of x is the acceleration, acceleration is
typically
defined by a, and keep in mind that this
is
all in one direction. It's in the x
direction
or the y direction. If you have
acceleration
up and the initial velocity is going to
somewhere
like the right, this formula will not
work.
And t is the time past, or delta-t, and
v of x is the final velocity. So this
is a really useful formula. When you have
three
values, for example, you have the final
velocity,
you have how long it accelerated for and
how
much it accelerated, you can easily find
its
initial velocity. Our second formula is
going
to be x equals x-initial.
By the way, this zero is naught, which
represents
the initial value. So this is the final x,
this
is the initial. This is the final
velocity,
this is its initial velocity before
anything
happened. Plus the initial velocity v
x-initial
times t plus one over two a
times t squared. And this is the formula
for
distance. So x, as you know, is final
distance.
x-initial is initial distance.
Sorry, it's final position, not distance.
Final
position, initial
position. And all these, you know,
velocity,
time past, acceleration. And
this is useful to find, calculate any
three
of these variables. Don't think that if
it's
pointing out x equals or v of x equals,
you
have to be solving for that. You can solve
for
any of these variables as long as you have
the
other ones. And the last formula will be v
of x squared, the final velocity, is equal
to
the initial velocity plus two a times
delta
x, which is the distance traveled.
So, and this one I find is really useful
and
I use it a lot in questions.
Sorry, my stylus here is tweaking a bit.
Distance, acceleration, initial velocity,
and
final velocity. And these
formulas are really, really helpful.
So I would either go on a site that has
these
three formulas or I would screenshot these
three
formulas and keep it for further use.
A good site I like to use is the AP
Physics
1 formula sheet. Even if you're not taking
1, it's really useful to have.
And also, I think that you are going to
keep
on revisiting these types of problems.
So these are basically like the holy
trinity
for physics. You will need these. And it's
good
to note that in all cases, unless it says
gravity
is neglected, there will be gravity.
Usually on Earth's surface, for example,
this
question, you will see it's being a ball
being
kicked. And then you have to take into
account
for the gravity of Earth. The gravity is
an
acceleration vector. It is 9.81 metres per
second
down. So if this is a ball, this would be
gravity.
9.81 metres per second down.
And this is a term, it's a constant that
you
must memorize. It's Earth's gravity.
And I feel like this right here is one of
the
most important things that you will ever
learn.